Last day.
[Music]
Charlotte and Wilbur were alone. The families had gone to look for Fern.
Templeton was asleep.
Wilbur lay resting after the excitement and strain of the ceremony. His medal
still hung from his neck. By looking out of the corner of his eye, he could see it.
"Charlott," said Wilbur after a while.
"Why are you so quiet?"
"I like to sit still," she said. "I've always been rather quiet." Yes, but you
seem specially so today. Do you feel all right? A little tired perhaps, but I
feel peaceful. Your success in the ring this morning was to a small degree my
success. Your future is assured. You will live secure and safe, Wilbur.
Nothing can harm you now.
These autumn days will shorten and grow cold. The leaves will shake loose from
the trees and fall. Christmas will come, then the snows of winter. You will live
to enjoy the beauty of the frozen world, for you mean a great deal to Zuckerman,
and he will not harm you ever. Winter will pass, the days will lengthen, the
ice will melt in the pasture pond.
The song sparrow will return and sing.
The frogs will awake. The warm wind will blow again. All these sights and sounds
and smells will be yours to enjoy, Wilbur. This lovely world, these precious days.
Charlotte stopped. A moment later, a tear came to Wilbur's eye. Oh,
Charlotte, he said, to think that when I first met you, I thought you were cruel
and bloodthirsty.
When he recovered from his emotion, he spoke again. "Why did you do all this
for me?" he asked. "I don't deserve it.
I've never done anything for you." "You have been my friend," replied Charlotte.
"That in itself is a tremendous thing. I wo my webs for you because I liked you.
After all, what's a life anyway? We're born, we live a little while, we die.
A spider's life can't help being something of a mess. With all this
trapping and eating flies by helping you, perhaps I was trying to lift up my
life a trifle. Heaven knows anyone's life can stand a little of that.
Well, said Wilbur, I'm no good at making speeches. I haven't got your gift for
words. But you have saved me, Charlotte.
And I would gladly give my life for you.
I really would.
I'm sure you would, and I thank you for your generous sentiments,
Charlotte, said Wilbur. We're all going home today. The fair is almost over.
Won't it be wonderful to be back home in the barn cellar again with the sheep and
the geese? Aren't you anxious to get home? For a moment, Charlotte said
nothing. Then she spoke in a voice so low could hardly hear the words.
"I will not be going back to the barn," she said. Wilbur leapt to his feet. "Not
going back," he cried. Charlotte, what are you talking about? I'm done for,"
she replied. "In a day or two, I'll be dead. I haven't even strength enough to
climb down into the crate. I doubt if I have enough silk in my spinets to lower
me to the ground."
Hearing this, Wilbur threw himself down in an agony of pain and sorrow. Great
sobs racked his body. He heaved and grunted with desolation.
Charlotte, he moaned. Charlotte, my true friend. Come now, let's not make a
scene, said the spider. Be quiet, Wilbur. Stop thrashing about.
But I can't stand it, shouted Wilbur. I won't leave you here alone to die. If
you're going to stay here, I shall stay, too.
Don't be ridiculous, said Charlotte. You can't stay here. Zuckerman and Lurvy and
John Arable and the others will be back any minute now, and they'll shove you
into that crate, and away you'll go.
Besides, it wouldn't make any sense for you to stay. There would be no one to
feed you. The fairgrounds will soon be empty and deserted.
Wilbur was in a panic. He raced round and round the pin. Suddenly, he had an
idea. He thought of the egg sack and the 514 little spiders that would hatch in
the spring. If Charlotte herself was unable to go home to the barn, at least
he must take her children along.
Wilbur rushed to the front of his pin.
He put his front feet up on the top board and gazed around. In the distance
he saw the arables and the Zuckermanman's approaching. He knew he
would have to act quickly. "Where's Templeton?" he demanded. "He's in that
corner under the straw, asleep," said Charlotte. Wilbur rushed over, pushed
his strong snout under the rat, and tossed him into the air.
"Tippleton!" screamed Wilbur. Pay attention.
The rat, surprised out of a sound sleep, looked first dazed, then disgusted.
"What kind of monkey shine is this?" he growled. "Can't the rat catch a wink of
sleep without being rudely popped into the air?" "Listen to me," cried Wilbur.
"Sharot is very ill. She has only a short time to live. She cannot accompany
us home because of her condition.
Therefore, it is absolutely necessary that I take her exac with me. I can't
reach it and I can't climb. You are the only one that can get it. There's not a
second to be lost. The people are coming. They'll be here in no time.
Please, please, please, Templeton, climb up and get the egg sack.
The rat yawned. He straightened his whiskers. Then he looked up at the egg
sack. "So he said in disgust."
"So it's old Templeton to the rescue again. Is it Templeton? Do this.
Templeton, do that. Templeton, please run down to the dump and get me a
magazine clipping. Templeton, please lend me a piece of string so I can spin a web."
Oh, hurry, said Wilbur. Hurry up, Templeton.
But the rat was in no hurry. He began imitating Wilbur's voice. So, it's Hurry
up, Templeton. Is it? He said, "And what thanks do I ever get for these
services? I would like to know." Never a kind word for old Templeton. only abuse
and wise cracks and side remarks. Never a kind word for a rat.
Templeton, said Wilbur in desperation, if you don't stop talking and get busy, all will be
lost, and I will die of a broken heart.
Please climb up." Templeton lay back in the straw. Lazily, he placed his foraws
behind his head and crossed his knees in an attitude of complete relaxation.
"I have a broken heart," he mimicked.
"How touching! My I noticed that it's always me you come
to when in trouble, but I have never heard of anyone's heartbreaking on my
account." Oh, no. Who cares anything about old Templeton?
Get up, screamed Wilbur. Stop acting like a spoiled child.
Templeton grinned and lay still. Who made trip after trip to the dump? He
asked. Why, it was old Templeton who saved Charlotte's life by scaring that
arable boy away with a rotten goose egg.
Bless my soul. I believe it was old Templeton. Who bit your tail and got you
back on your feet this morning after you had fainted in front of the crowd? Old Templeton?
Has it ever occurred to you that I'm sick of running errands and doing
favors? What do you think I am anyway? A rat of Volwick?
Wilbur was desperate. The people were coming and the rat was failing him.
Suddenly, he remembered Templeton's fondness for food. "Timultton," he said,
"I will make you a solemn promise.
"Get Charlotte's egg sack for me, and from now on, I will let you eat first
when Lurvy slops me. I will let you have your choice of everything in the trough,
and I won't touch a thing until you're through." The rat sat up. You mean that?
He said, "I promise I cross my heart."
"All right, it's a deal," said the rat.
He walked to the wall and started to climb.
His stomach was still swollen from last night's gorge. Groaning and complaining,
he pulled himself slowly to the ceiling.
He crept along till he reached the egg sack.
Charlotte moved aside for him. She was dying, but she still had strength enough
to move a little. Then Templeton bared his long, ugly teeth and began snipping
the threads that fastened the sack to the ceiling.
Wilbur watched from below. "Use extreme care," he said. "I don't want a single
one of those eggs harmed." This rough sticks in my mouth, complained the rat.
It's worse than caramel candy. But Templeton worked away at the job and
managed to cut the sack a drift and carry it to the ground where he dropped
it in front of Wilbur. Wilbur heaved a great sigh of relief.
"Thank you, Templeton," he said. "I will never forget this as long as I live."
Neither will I, said the rat, picking his teeth. I feel as though I'd eaten a
spool of thread. Well, home we go.
Templeton crept into the crate and buried himself in the straw. He got out
of sight just in time. Lurvy and John Arabel and Mr. Zuckerman came along at
that moment, followed by Mrs. Arable and Mrs. Zuckerman and Avery and Fern.
Wilbur had already decided how he would carry the egg sack. There was only one
way possible. He carefully took the little bundle in his mouth and held it
there on top of his tongue. He remembered what Charlotte had told him,
that the sack was waterproof and strong.
It felt funny on his tongue and made him drool a bit, and of course he couldn't
say anything.
But as he was being shoved into the crate, he looked up at Charlotte and
gave her a wink. She knew he was saying goodbye in the only way he could, and
she knew her children were safe.
"Goodbye," she whispered. Then she summoned all her strength and waved one
of her front legs at him.
She never moved again.
Next day, as the ferris wheel was being taken apart and the raceh horses were
being loaded into vans and the entertainers were packing up their
belongings and driving away in their trailers, Charlotte died.
The fairgrounds were soon deserted. The sheds and buildings were empty and
forlorn. The infield was littered with bottles and trash. Nobody of the
hundreds of people that had visited the fair knew that a gray spider had played
the most important part of all. No one was with her when she died.